A Guide to the Executive communications of the Office of the Speaker, 1776-1864
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Executive communications of the Office of the Speaker, 1776-1864
The Library of Virginia
36912
13.7 cu. ft. (29 boxes)
Virginia. General Assembly. House of Delegates. Speaker.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Use the microfilm or digital copies instead of the originals.
Acquisition Information
Transferred on an unknown date from the House Speaker's Office, State Capitol, Richmond, VA.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on film (Misc. Reels 5372-5396] and online at Digital Collections Discovery
Biographical Information
The House of Delegates' predecessor, the House of Burgesses, was modeled after the House of Commons, in Parliament. The House of Burgesses existed from 1643 to 1776. The first session of the General Assembly, which took place in 1776, established the first constitution and made the House of Delegates the most powerful branch in state government. It was not until the constitution of 1851 was adopted that a more equitable balance among the branches of government was established. In the General Assembly, members of the House of Delegates and the Senate vote on legislation entered during the legislative session. Legislative bills can originate either in the House of Delegates or in the Senate, with both chambers having the ability to establish study committees. Each serves as a check upon the other to ensure a thorough debate on the merits of each bill. Currently the House of Delegates, together with the Senate, meets as the General Assembly in annual session, alternatively during thirty to sixty days. Currently there are 100 members of the House of Delegates, each representing a voting district in the Commonwealth.
Scope and Content
The Executive Communications contain correspondence to the Speaker of the House of Delegates between 1776 and 1864. This collection should not be confused with the Executive Papers which contain incoming correspondence directly to the Governor's Office. The Executive Communications, however, complement the Executive Papers by reiterating many of the central issues facing the Commonwealth. In addition, correspondence from the Governor often includes letters, accounts, petitions, proceedings, reports, returns, resolutions, and other documents for the consideration of the General Assembly. In some cases, these documents are the original item received by the Governor. In other cases, the documents are copies of the originals transcribed by the Assistant Clerk of the Council of State. In still other cases, the Governor's enclosure can no longer be found.
Each item has been cataloged individually and can be found in the catalog or online at the Library of Virginia's Digital Collections Discovery.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Executive communications, 1776-1779 (Box 1)
- Executive communications, 1780-1782 November (Box 2)
- Executive communications, 1782 December-1785 (Box 3)
- Executive communications, 1786-1788 October (Box 4)
- Executive communications, 1788 November-1790 (Box 5)
- Executive communications, 1791-1793 (Box 6)
- Executive communications, 1794-1799 (Box 7)
- Executive communications, 1800-1803 (Box 8)
- Executive communications, 1804-1807 (Box 9)
- Executive communications, 1808-1810 (Box 10)
- Executive communications, 1811-1813 May (Box 11)
- Executive communications, 1813 December-1819 (Box 12)
- Executive communications, 1820-1824 (Box 13)
- Executive communications, 1825-1831 (Box 14)
- Executive communications, 1831 December 6 (Box 14a)
- Executive communications, 1832-1842 (Box 15)
- Executive communications, 1843-1864 (Box 16)
- Executive communications, 1775-1864 (Box 17)
- Executive communications, 1775-1864 (Box 18)
- Executive communications [oversize], 1777-1785 (Box 19)
- Executive communications [oversize], 1786-1788 November (Box 20)
- Executive communications [oversize], 1788 December-1790 (Box 21)
- Executive communications [oversize], 1791-1792 (Box 22)
- Executive communications [oversize], 1793-1797 (Box 23)
- Executive communications [oversize], 1798-1802 (Box 24)
- Executive communications [oversize], 1803-1806 (Box 25)
- Executive communications [oversize], 1807-1813 February (Box 26)
- Executive communications [oversize], 1813 May-1822 (Box 27)
- Executive communications [oversize], 1823-1834 (Box 28)
- Executive communications [oversize], 1838-1862 (Box 29)